Guide to the Cedric N. Chatterley Photographs, 1983-2013 and undated RL.00219
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Spencer, South Dakota Series, 1998-2008, 7 boxes; 268 prints
  - 11x14 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints, 192 prints
    - Nancy Webb (far right) giving her husband, Lloyd, a ceramic figure of a man pushing his car out of a bank of snow, McCook County, South Dakota, three miles north of Spencer, Christmas Day, 1998 (Box 22, Print 104)
      She was teasing him for all the times he got farm and family vehicles stuck in the mud and snow. Nancy's sister, Myrta, is center--Christmas tree in background. The stairwell in the farmhouse.
    - Lloyd Webb working to thaw a water line in the north pasture, McCook County, South Dakota, the week between Christmas and New Year, 1998 (Box 22, Print 105)
      A dead and frozen cow carcass, lower right.
    - Richard Stone looking into the basement bathroom that is under construction, Spencer, South Dakota, New Years Day, 1999 (Box 22, Print 106)
      Behind him is the temporary cardboard door that closes onto the nails (right).
    - Richard Stone showing the ring he will give to his girlfriend. In a temporary room made for him in the southwest corner of the basement, Spencer, South Dakota, New Years Day, 1999 (Box 22, Print 107)
    - On Interstate 90, heading east towards Sioux Fall, South Dakota after visiting Spencer on New Year's Day, 1999 (Box 22, Print 109)
      My father's 1981 VW pickup. I found the doll head on the ground at the Webb's.
    - Suzy Webb sleeping, Lloyd driving, near Epiphany, South Dakota, January 9, 1999 (Box 22, Print 110)
      We were going back to the Webb's farm after getting some furniture out of storage on a farm northeast of Spencer--some friends of the Webb's.
    - Nancy Webb stepping across the newly installed kitchen floor tiles, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, April, 2000 (Box 22, Print 161)
      Heating elements were placed beneath. The farmhouse is on the land that her grandfather homesteaded.
    - Nancy Webb wiping up the newly installed tiles in the farmhouse kitchen floor, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, April, 2000 (Box 22, Print 162)
      Heating elements were placed beneath.
    - Lloyd Webb working on the starter for his 1952 Chevy. Nancy's dog, Richard Nixon, nearby, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, April, 2000 (Box 22, Print 163)
      Suzy and Bridgette by the propane tank. At the farmhouse.
    - Powder and Suzy Webb running near the farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, April, 2000 (Box 22, Print 164)
      The concrete foundation (left) was part of the barn that had been destroyed by a tornado in 1969. The barn, Lloyd said, could be seen from Highway 38 nearly 4 miles away.
    - Kara and Brandon Stone during his 2nd birthday party, Spencer, South Dakota, May 1, 2000 (Box 22, Print 165)
    - Jason Fredricks and Jessica Twedt after vows were exchanged. First Lutheran Church in downtown, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, September 30, 2000 (Box 22, Print 166)
    - Lloyd Webb and his dog, Powder (one of several farm pets), on Lloyd's 45th birthday, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer, March 23, 2002 (Box 22, Print 167)
      Out in the barn, on the farm. It was around 25 to 30 degrees that day in the barn.
    - Dave Twedt with his granddaughter, Kaitlyn, on his 47th birthday. In the kitchen at home, Spencer, South Dakota, May 4, 2002 (Box 22, Print 168)
    - Danny Stone in the northwest corner of his yard the day he turned 42 years old, Spencer, South Dakota, June 11, 2002 (Box 22, Print 169)
    - Nancy and Lloyd Webb preparing to shoot at targets in the north pasture (Lloyd as a sergeant at the South Dakota State Penitentiary in Sioux Falls, July, 2002 (Box 22, Print 170)
      Their marriage would begin to dissolve the following year. Three negatives printed consecutively.
    - Richard Stone in his basement apartment, the corner of South Dakota Avenue and 18th Street, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July, 2002 (Box 22, Print 171)
      The building no longer exists--it was condemned and razed the following year.
    - Richard Stone in his basement apartment in Sioux Falls, South Dakota, late July, 2002 (Box 22, Print 172)
      Unemployed and behind in his rent.
    - Nancy Webb making pizza dough at the farmhouse, 3 miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, May 17, 2003 (Box 22, Print 173)
      We were celebrating Nancy's 47th birthday (May 16).
    - Nancy Webb helping her grandson, Isaac, with his pedal car, McCook County, South Dakota--three miles north of Spencer at the family farm, May 17, 2003 (Box 22, Print 174)
      This was Saturday, May 17, 2003 and we were celebrating Nancy's 47th birthday (May 16). The sink, to the left, was at one time down the hall from my Sioux Falls studio space. I used it when washing prints.
    - Lloyd Webb and his grandson, Issac, at the barn entrance, McCook County--three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, May 17, 2003 (Nancy's birthday party) (Box 22, Print 175)
      Lloyd was pulling ticks off Powder (the white dog) and Issac was smashing them. Richard Nixon, Nancy's dog, watches.
    - Kaitlyn Ann (Peanut) at her dance school's dress rehearsal, on stage at the Riad Shrine Auditorium in downtown Sioux Falls, South Dakota, May 17, 2003 (Box 22, Print 176)
    - With Dave and Mary Twedt's home to my back--facing east/southeast, corner of Highway 38 and County Road 431, May 30, 2003 (Box 22, Print 177)
      Five years to the day when a F-4 tornado destroyed most of Spencer, South Dakota (about 1/2 mile north of this location). Winds to 50 mph were reported in Sioux Falls on the day this photograph was made.
    - Paityn, the smallest, and Kaitlyn, Jessica (left), Doris Westerman (the kids' great-grandmother/Mary's mother) and Mary Twedt (right), 1512 S. Olive Drive, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 2003 (Box 22, Print 178)
      Katie's 4th birthday. In Al and Doris Westerman's backyard.
    - Kaitlyn Anne Fredricks ("Peanut") at a party for her 4th birthday, July 19, 2003 (Box 22, Print 179)
      We are at Al and Doris Westerman's in Sioux Falls, South Dakota. The Westermans are Mary Twedt's parents, making them Peanut's great-grandparents. Mary is left, with Paityn over her shoulder.
    - Kaitlyn Anne (Peanut) and Paityn, right, running in Dave and Mary Twedt's front area, the corner of County Road 431 and South Dakota Hwy 38, McCook County, South Dakota, May 30, 2004 (Box 22, Print 180)
      Six years to the day from the Spencer tornado.
    - Kaitlyn with her dolls, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 2004 (Box 22, Print 181)
      We were celebrating Peanut's 5th birthday (July 19). This was the same year Jessica divorced Kaitlyn's father, Jayson Fredricks.
    - Jessica, shortly before marrying Tony Byre in Brandon, South Dakota, May 14, 2005 (Box 23, Print 182)
      Jessica is the only child of Dave and Mary Twedt.
    - Kaitlyn, with arms outstretched, at Jessica and Tony's wedding reception. (Her mother's second marriage.) Near Beaver Creek, Minnesota, May 17, 2005 (Box 23, Print 183)
      Jessica and Tony Byre were married earlier that day in Brandon, South Dakota.
    - Mary Twedt sweeping up after 100 mph straight line winds blew the roof off their home the night before (August 2), McCook County, South Dakota, August 4, 2004 (Box 23, Print 184)
    - Kaitlyn Fredricks and Mary Twedt (Kaitlyn's grandmother) atop the Twedt's home, June, 2005 (Box 23, Print 185)
      Dave and Mary were in the process of rebuilding a part of their roof that had been blown off the year before (Spencer can be seen in the distance).
    - Paityn (with braid) and Kaitlyn (Katy, or Peanut) at their grandmother's, Betty Twedt, 801 West Avenue, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, July 19, 2005 (Box 23, Print 186)
      Katy is looking out the window of what was once their grandfather's bedroom (Dave Twedt). Katy's 6th birthday.
    - Mary and Dave Twedt sharing a laugh with Reverend Ward Satterly, who is visiting from North Dakota during Spencer's 125th Anniversary celebration (we were in the Catholic Parish Center), July 18, 2005 (Box 23, Print 187)
      The Reverend's wife was one of six deaths during the May 30, 1998 tornado... He married Kara and Danny Stone in September, 1998... A sign on the Parish Center's door advertised free lots to those who would build in Spencer.
    - Spencer, South Dakota celebrating 125 years of existence, June 18, 2005 (Box 23, Print 188)
      The local firemen are competing with one another to see who can spray the barrel to the opposite end of the suspended rope.
    - Local celebrating the 125th anniversary of Spencer, South Dakota, June 18, 2005 (Box 23, Print 189)
    - Danny Stone working on his lawn mower, Spencer, South Dakota, June 18, 2005--the 125th anniversary of Spencer (Box 23, Print 190)
    - Kaitlyn ("Peanut") at work in Dave and Mary Twedt's garden (her grandparents), Memorial Day Weekend, 2006 (8 years since the May 30, 1998 tornado) (Box 23, Print 191)
      About 1/2 mile south of Spencer, South Dakota, the intersection of South Dakota Highway 38 and McCook County Road 431.
    - Kaitlyn, holding her dance outfit, and her sister, Paityn, with their great-grandmother, Betty Twedt, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, June, 2006 (Box 23, Print 192)
      (June Thompson and I lived 3 blocks away.)
    - Breyton, Paityn, Mary Twedt and Katie playing "hillbilly golf" in front of Dave and Mary's home south of Spencer, South Dakota, June, 2008 (Box 23, Print 193)
      Hillbilly golf is a game played with two golf balls attached by a string of 18 inch rope. Each player has a set of three, and they toss them one at a time to one of two "gates" set about 20 feet apart. When a flopping string of golf balls catches a rung and stays on or wraps itself around, points are awarded: 3 points for the top, 2 for the middle, 1 for the bottom. The player who gets 21 points first wins.
    - Kaitlyn Ann Fredricks ("Peanut") rounding third base, Spencer, South Dakota, July 2, 2008 (Box 23, Print 194)
    - Kaitlyn and Paityn in the swimming pool behind Dave and Mary Twedt's, the weekend before school started, August 16, 2008 (8x10 contact print) (Box 23, Print 195)
      The pool had been part of the Golden Pheasant Restaurant and Lounge. The building Dave and Mary made into a home following the Spencer tornado on May 30, 1998. Image made with a handbuilt 8x10 camera, fitted with a 100 year old lens.
    - Kaitlyn ("Peanut", center) and her friend Brooklin from Spencer (left) helping Mary Twedt prepare her Home and Garden Party Brochures. At Dave and Mary Twedt's home, corner of Highway 38 and County Road 431, McCook County, South Dakota, August 16, 2008 (Box 23, Print 196)
      Mary has been hosting Home and Garden Parties in private homes, school fundraisers, etc, for a second income. 5x7 contact print from handmade, handheld camera.
    - Craig Leach (neighbor) and Jenna Webb behind her home in Spencer, South Dakota, August, 2008 (8x10 print) (Box 23, Print 197)
    - Brandon Stone listening to the after-game speech given by his coach, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, August 23, 2008 (Box 23, Print 198)
      His Junior League football team from Salem, South Dakota had just played their first competitive game of the season. The opposing, more experienced team won... Four years earlier, Brandon, his mother, Kara and his two younger sisters, Rebecca and Tiffany, were involved in a rollover accident about a mile from Spencer. He kicked out the window of the minivan and ran a 1/4 mile in stocking feet through the snow and ice to get help, essentially saving her life.
    - Suzy Webb being escorted down the aisle of St Mary's Catholic Church in Salem, South Dakota, by her mother, Nancy Webb, September 27, 2008 (Box 23, Print 199)
      (Daughter, mother, Virgin Mary.)
    - Suzy Webb's wedding reception, the National Guard Armory in Salem, South Dakota, September 27, 2008 (Box 23, Print 200)
      Her father, Lloyd Webb, is in the doorway. (Suzy was adopted by the Webb's when she was a child. Lloyd and Nancy had several foster children come and go from their home. Jenna--not pictured--was their only biological child.)
    - Alexa Roth (the daughter of Vicki, a foster child Lloyd and Nancy raised) by the water tank in the north pasture, 200 yards from the farmhouse, McCook County, three miles north of Spencer, South Dakota, September 29, 2008 (Box 23, Print 201)
      We were taking a break between Suzy Webb's wedding and the reception to be held later that evening. This is the first time Nancy had seen Lloyd in two and a half years.
    - The enigmatic Lloyd Webb (Vicki and Nancy in the background, the north pasture), McCook County, South Dakota, September 27, 2008 (Box 23, Print 202)
      I had not seen Lloyd in nearly four years--about the time he and Nancy divorced. When this image was made, he was living in Sheldon, Iowa, an hour and a half from Sioux Falls and working in an ethanol plant. I once thought of him as my closest friend in South Dakota... Many people thought the tornado had hardly fazed Lloyd, and they were probably correct. But nobody in his family called and asked how he was in the weeks that followed the storm... This image was made the day Suzy Webb married her high school boyfriend, Mike... Lloyd had not been out to the farm in nearly three years. It was hard to know what he was thinking.
    - Lloyd and Nancy Webb following the horses back to the farmhouse, McCook County, South Dakota, September 27, 2008 (Box 23, Print 203)
      Later that evening they will attend Suzy and Mike's wedding reception in Salem, ten miles east. Nancy's grandfather, Tillotson, homesteaded this land shortly before South Dakota became a state in 1889.
    - Nancy Webb returning one of her two doves to its cage, September, 2008 (Box 23, Print 204)
      We were in the stairwell landing of the farmhouse, about an hour after Suzy Webb's wedding.
    - Most of Suzy Webb and Mike's wedding party, the National Guard Armory, Salem, South Dakota, September 27, 2008 (Box 23, Print 205)
      From left to right: Jenna Webb and Craig; Nancy and Lloyd Webb; Alexa and DJ (Vicki's children); Mike and Suzy; Isaac (Jenna's son); Vicki and her husband; Derrick; and Myrta Wold, Nancy Webb's sister.
    - My god-daughter, Kaitlyn Ann Fredricks (Peanut), riding in the passenger seat of my 1993 Toyota Camry, heading west on 33rd Street, approaching Minnesota Avenue, on our way back to Grandma Betty's (Dave Twedt's mother) where Peanut spends the night on dance nights, Sioux Falls, South Dakota, September, 2008 (Box 23, Print 206)
      (I've been taking Peanut to and from her dance lessons since she was five years old.)
  - 16x20 gelatin silver selenium-toned prints, 14 prints
    - The doors to the National Guard Armory, Salem, South Dakota (10 miles East of Spencer), June 1998 (Box 25, Print 44)
    - A backhoe operator from California picking up rubble across from the grain elevator in Spencer, June 1998 (Box 25, Print 42)
    - South Dakota Department of Corrections inmates working to clean up Spencer from the May 30, 1998 F-4 tornado, June 1998 (Box 25, Print 33)
    - Rain, wipers on the windshield of my 1981 VW pickup, heading East on SD Highway 38 between Spencer and Salem, June, 1998 (Box 25, Print 34)
    - Reverend Thomas Christopher standing on what is left at the Trinity Lutheran Church in Spencer, June 1998 (Box 25, Print 26)
      Thomas (in center with horn) has momentarily borrowed the horn from the boy standing next to him. This was about an hour before a church service was held on this floor to celebrate the old church and to plan a new one on the same location. The banner reads: On Him Alone We Build.
    - Inside the fallen water tower in Spencer (from the May 30 tornado), June 1998 (Box 25, Print (unnumbered))
    - Bernie Opland (seated inside the skip loader) and a friend who came out for the day gathering tornado damaged vehicles to crush in Bernie's portable car crusher, June 1998 (Box 25, Print 210)
      Close to 200 vehicles were crushed and hauled away by Bernie following the May 30 tornado.
    - Spencer, South Dakota's Cardinals -- the PeeWee League, July 2008 (Box 25, Print 209)
      The kids Chatterley knows are Rebecca Stone (far left), Paityn Fredricks (fourth from left), Kaitlyn Fredricks (eighth from left), Breyton Fredricks (next to Kaitlyn, front). Chad Mentle is the coach (wearing sunglasses). This image was shot at Spencer's ballfield is in the Northeast part of town.
    - Standing in Dave and Mary Twedt's backyard area and looking toward Spencer on the 10 year anniversary of Spencer's tornado, May 2008 (Box 25, Print 208)
      This photograph was made with Chatterley's hand-made camera fitted with a 100 mm lens removed from a plastic camera.
    - Men taking down a VFW flag in the back at a pickup truck following a parade to celebrate the 125th anniversary of Spencer, June 2005 (Box 25, Print 207)
    - Riding with Lloyd Webb in the North pasture (3 miles North of Spencer), passing a frozen pond, March 1999 (Box 25, Print 121)
    - Standing on the platform where the old Spencer water tower stood, facing Southeast, New Year's Day, 1999 (Box 25, Print 108)
      The home in the center of the photograph belongs to Cookie Mentle. Her son Troy once owned the car in the driveway. Troy, Richard Stone, and another boy were fishing during the day of the May 30, 1998 tornado. They were in Troy's garage cleaning fish when Troy saw the tornado coming into town. He managed to get himself, Richard and the other boy into a storm cellar just seconds before the tornado passed over them. Richard Stone credits Troy for saving his life. Troy died the following Halloween weekend from liver failure due to excessive drinking. He was living an apartment in Sioux Falls, South Dakota. I spoke to him on the phone just a few days before. His name is present on the tornado memorial in town along with the six others who passed on May 30, 1998. The Stones' house is in the distance to the left.
    - Burning discarded buiding material and rubbish in front of Lloyd and Nancy Webb's farm house, 3 miles north of Spencer, the day before Thanksgiving, 1998 (Box 25, Print 93)
    - A few spot "test" fires that have been lit in the rubble following the razing of most of Spencer, June 1998 (Box 25, Print 54)
      This is one of two large trenches dug to accept the tornado damaged town following the May 30, 1998 tornado, June 1998
  - Work prints, 62 prints
    - Work prints, 11x14 inches, gelatin silver, undated (Box 25)
- Triangle Residential Options for Substance Abusers, 2002 and undated, 1 box; 14 prints
  Founded in 1994, the Durham, North Carolina based Triangle Residential Options for Substance Abusers (TROSA) is a multi-year residential program that enables substance abusers to be productive, recovering individuals by providing comprehensive treatment, work-based vocational training, education, and continuing care. Chatterley's photographs document the program and its residents in the spring and summer of 2002. Consists of one 11x14 print, two 6x20 prints, and eleven 16x20 prints, all selenium-toned gelatin silver prints. Captions were created by the photographer; prints are in original order as received.
  - 11x14 print of William Mack or "Mr. Mac." Head of the TROSA brick laying crew (staff) at his home in Durham, North Carolina, 2002 (Box 26)
  - 6x20 panorama print of New TROSA resident trying on clothes in the TROSA warehouse. Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Spring (3 negatives printed consecutively) (Box 26)
  - 6x20 panorama print of TROSA resident prior to graduation ceremony (2 year program). National Guard Armory, Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Spring (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of the TROSA band during rehearsal. ("T-West") Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Spring (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA staff and residents (Kevin McDonald, Director, is closest to camera). Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Aug. (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA residents gathering before graduation ceremony. National Guard Armory, Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Aug. (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA graduates. National Guard Armory, Durham, North Carolina, 2002 Aug. (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA garage and donated cars to residents who are about to graduate from the program. "T-West" Durham, North Carolina, 2002 (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of Learning to make biscuits. T-North (TROSA) Triangle Residential Options for Substance Abusers, Durham, NC, 2002 (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA resident with One Year Medal-"T-North" Durham, North Carolina, undated (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA moving crew at Duke University (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of Mr. Mac (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print of TROSA kitchen staff (Box 26)
  - 16x20 print, untitled and undated, of a group of workers sitting on a stoop (Box 26)
- Sheep Ranching in Montana, 2004-2005, 2013, 2 boxes; 97 prints
  Scope and Contents
  Series explores the intense work of sheep ranching during lambing season, with photographs taken by Chatterley near Greenough, Montana, United States, in the spring seasons of 2004 and 2005. The series focuses on rancher Judith Faye "Pachy" Burns, who ran the operation with the help of friends, daughters, shearers, and a migrant worker family from Perú. The photographer's own niece was also helping out at the time the series was shot. Pachy Burns passed away some years later. After her death, Chatterley visited her daughters, Bluesette Campbell and Piney Hardiman, and their father, in Red Lodge and Scotch Coulee, Montana, in 2013; there he took six more photographs, and recorded oral histories concerning Pachy Burns, her family, and her life as a rancher.
  All of the 97 black-and-white selenium-toned prints measure 16x20 inches. Captions were created by the photographer.
  - My niece, Felice Austin (at left) and Pachy Burns (at right) pulling a lamb/catching a lamb. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 1)
  - Pachy Burns (at left) and Felice Austin (at right) sorting lambs and sheep. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 2)
  - Fran Woody holding a lamb at the docking table, Pachy Burns with knife/scraper. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring 2004. Fran was from Ohio, and was a very active participant in "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 3)
  - Pachy Burns "banding" a lamb's tail so it will eventually fall off. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 4)
  - Fran Woody (at left), Pachy Burns (at right) and my niece, Felice Austin (at right). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 5)
  - Fran Woody (left), Louise Swartzwalder (center) and Pachy Burns. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004 "Jam to Lamb." We were out walking, looking for anything that might harm the sheep (barbed wire pieces, etc.) and Fran is holding a sheep's tail she found--among many to be found. (Box 28, Image 6)
  - Pachy Burns and Esteban Lozano, Sr. helping with a difficult birth. Esteban comes from Peru and has worked with Pachy nearly year-round. He also has his sons come up from Peru to help--Esteban, Jr., Ricky, and Rufo. (Box 28, Image 7)
  - Pachy Burns reaching in for a lamb, Esteban Lozano, Sr. and Esteban, Jr. holding on. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring 2004. (Box 28, Image 8)
    Image is meant to be vertical.
  - Pachy Burns with the head of a new born lamb. Esteban Lozano Sr. and Jr. watch. Near Greenough, Montana--Spring, 2004. (Box 28, Image 9)
    Image is meant to be horizontal.
  - Pachy Burns reaching in to help with a difficult birth. The painted/ink brand is for "Blue Pines Ranch" (Pachy's brand). Near Greenough, Montana--Spring 2004 "Jam to Lamb." (Box 28, Image 10)